Guide to the Joseph James Mathews Papers, 1930-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph James Mathews papers 1930-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mathews, Joseph James.
4.0 linear feet Extent: 4,184 Items
Chairman of the Emory History Department starting in 1948. Collection spans Dr. Mathews' career as a professor of European history. He taught at the University of Chattanooga, University of Mississippi, and Emory University. He served as historian in the armed forces during World War II; during his time at the Naval Bureau of Ordnance and Ordnance Activities he directed and authored numerous studies and publications. His vitae is included in the collection. The papers primarily consist of Mathew's personal and professional correspondence. The personal letters reflect his professional interests and activities while the professional letters deal with personnel, budgets, curricula, and his service for the Southern Historical Association, among other topics. There are about three dozen wartime photos, and volumes of class rolls.
RL.00884
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joseph James Mathews Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1976.
Biographical Note
Joseph James Mathews was a professor of European History and Chairman of the Emory History Department starting in 1948.
Collection Overview
Collection spans Dr. Mathews' career as a professor of European history. He taught at the University of Chattanooga, University of Mississippi, and Emory University. He served as historian in the armed forces during World War II. At the Naval Bureau of Ordnance and Ordnance Activities he directed and authored numerous studies and publications. His vitae is included in the collection. The collection holds primarily Mathew's personal and professional correspondence. The personal letters reflect his professional interests and activities while the professional letters deal with personnel, budgets, curricula, and his service for the Southern Historical Association, among other topics. There are about three dozen wartime photos, and volumes of class rolls. Photographs and political cartoons in box 10 relate to World War II, the Zulu War, the United States Civil War, and conflict in Sudan. See also the Marcia (Mayfield) Mathews (Mrs. Joseph J.) Papers.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Mathews, Joseph James; Mathews, Marcia M.; United States. Navy -- Ordnance and ordnance stores; Emory University; University of Mississippi; University of Chattanooga; Southern Historical Association; Ordnance, Naval; World War, 1939-1945; Photographs; Political cartoons
Related Material
Marcia M. Mathews Papers, 1833-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Joseph James Mathews Papers, 1930-1976, (10 boxes)
  - Professional Papers, 1947-1956 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
  - Professional Papers, 1952-1960 (Box 2)
  - Professional Papers, 1961-1974 (Box 3)
  - Professional Papers, 1974-1976 and undated (Box 4)
  - Notebooks and Class Rolls, 1936-1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1947 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1951 June (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1951 July-1957 Apr. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1957 May-1965 and undated (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1976 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, Navy photographs, and political cartoons (Box 10)